who doesn't want to freeze themselves to
screamworthy pain to shed a few
kilograms of body fat you're in luck
because I've got the video for you
seriously though there's a study that's
made the rounds on the effect that cold
water immersion and discovered some
pretty remarkable effects in humans
that's you fortunately you don't have to
freeze to death to achieve these results
but let's get into the details the idea
behind Cold Water immersion is to
subject your body to Coal to stimulate
the generation of brown fat cells brown
adipocytes or fat cells are unique from
the typical white adipocytes because
they are extremely energetically
inefficient in the case of overall fat
loss that's a very good thing the less
efficient cells are the more energy that
they waste causing them the need to take
up and utilize more fat molecules to
make more energy if this happens
repeatedly your white fat where most of
your body fat is housed will be slowly
depleted of fat molecules turning you
into Timothy Shalom even if not quite
literally the point is you'll be lean in
addition there's an inverse relationship
between brown atopos tissue and
cardiometabolic disease meaning the more
Brown fat in your body the less cardom
metabolic disease that's an association
though just to be clear there's a lot
more here from how you're nervous system
activates these Brown fat cells through
the release of neurotransmitter nor
epinephrine binding receptors known as
beta adrenergic receptors on the fat
cells but we'll leave that b for now the
overall point is that more Brown fat is
linked to higher likelihood to lose
overall body fat and have improved
Health okay so what did the researchers
do and what did they find essentially
they compared two groups of people
against one another they recruited
people who regularly engage in Winter
swimming versus people who don't they
match the groups by age weight physical
activity and multiple other factors
between the groups at least the best
that they could then they exposed both
groups the winter swimmers and the
non-insane people I mean the control
group my apologies to cold water and
warm in a regulated Manner and performed
a series of measures to tease out
different
okay so first did they experience
changes in their Brown fat actually yeah
we see that here this is a measure of
blood sugar uptake by the brown fat
cells the green on the left are the
control group and the right side the
purple are the
massicus I'm sorry I meant the winter
swimmers TC there stands for thermal
comfort so at a warm temperature not
freezing their buns off the cooling is
when they were exposed to cold therapy
if the dots and lines go up that means
that more blood sugar was taken up by
the brown fat cells as we can see
relative to the thermal Comfort
condition cooling increased blood sugar
uptake for both groups I can even show
you a picture of what that looks like
here notice that the dark splotches
around the neck the clavicle and the
sternum for when these people are cooled
that's the glucose the sugar Tracer
uptake it's pretty neat in fact if we
look at an oral glucose tolerance test a
test where the researchers are measuring
the ability for the cells of the body to
clear blood sugar from the body at the
end of the test the winter swimmers had
lower overall blood glucose compared to
the control group although they started
at the same point we can reconcile the
difference here and not in the brown fat
cell glucose uptake data that we just
went over because it's likely that the
winter swimmers have a greater absolute
amount of brown fat cells at least
that's my educated guess now all that
leads us to the most unbelievable
results if we look at the actual energy
expenditure otherwise stated as total
metabolism you'll note that there's no
difference between the two groups when
at a comfortable warm temperature but
there's a significant increase in
metabolism when Cooling in addition the
winter swimmers have an even more robust
effect we can see that more easily
Quantified here A near 500 calorie boost
in the controls and a near 1,000 calorie
boost in the winter swimmers those are
massive effects the researchers point
out that this is not all explained by
greater activity of brown fat and in
fact they show some evidence that muscle
activity is increased as well still
regardless of the responsible tissue
these effects are
unbelievable and that's exactly why I'm
having a tough time believing this to be
clear I'm not denying the data but even
the researchers point out that other
Studies have indicated very mild
increases in total Metabolism from Brown
fat tissue in humans sometimes like 50
times less which is why the researchers
point out that there may be something
else going on here like the muscle
activity angle but they also speculate
that other Studies have looked at people
in their 30s and these individuals of
this study that we're in uh are in 20s I
got to admit I don't buy that for a
millisecond I've never seen a 50-fold
difference between 20 and 30 year olds
but maybe that's just me grasping at
days gone by in
desperation I think what we can say is
that metabolism does increase regardless
and it might truly be by that astounding
of a magnitude even if the effect is not
solely driven by Brown fat if you're one
of those masochists that wants more more
details on the cold immersion protocols
used just to jump on over to the
physionic Insiders I'll be putting it
all together there for you plus you get
access to all my work step-by-step
guides premium podcasts and much more
it's linked in the description for you
so what's the takeaway here the takeaway
is that cold immersion helps insulin
sensitivity as we saw with improved
glucose tolerance test which was seen
with no differences in insulin by the
way we also know that cold immersion
increases metabolism partly due to Brown
fat cell activity it seems so if you're
inclined to expose yourself to very cold
several times per week you might reap
some pretty significant benefits
although I would like to see some of the
results here replicated either way the
one thing that I do know with 100%
certainty is that another video of mine
is painless to experience unlike cold
immersion unless you hated this video in
which case it's a toss up I'll see you
over there
[Music]